片名：国王与我
本版本字幕由 Wendy's PaPa 翻译、整理、调校时间轴
This version subtitles by Wendy's PaPa
泰国 1862年
快点搬，快点搬，不能整天耗在这
Come on, lads, hurry!
We haven't got all day.
船长，这就是泰国了吗
Is that it, captain? Are we here?
对，这就是曼谷
Aye, laddie. That's Bangkok all right.
路易，路易
Louis! Oh, Louis!
妈妈，曼谷到了
Mother! Look, there's Bangkok.
我知道，这真令人兴奋
Yes, I know. Isn't it exciting?
船长，告诉我为什么要抛下锚呢
有什么问题吗？
Captain, I heard them lowering
the anchor. ls anything wrong?
我们在等待涨潮，只有那时才能入港
We have to wait for the afternoon
tide to carry us over the bar.
原来是这样
Oh, I see.
妈妈，不知道国王会不会来接我们？
Will the king of Siam come down
to meet us, Mother?
我想当然不会来了，国王不会的，这有规矩
I hardly think so, dear.
Kings don't, as a rule.
船头人手不足，快去
Come forward, lads.
They need help in the bow.
快去那里
Get along there.
那是皇室的船
That's the royal barge.
国王来接我们了吗
The king is coming out to meet us.
没有，是克拉拉贺
It's not the king, it's the Oklahoma.
克拉拉贺是谁
Who is the kralahome?
他是首相
A sort of a prime minister.
应该是国王的助手吧
The king's right-hand man, you might say.
让我看一下好吗，看一下
May I look? Please, may I see?
夫人，我提醒你
Aye, laddie.
最好对他小心点
Ma'am, if I might be allowed to offer
you a word of warning,
因为他是一个很有权利的人
that man has power, and he can
use it for you or against you.
跟他作对，后果不堪设想
You must stop worrying about me,
Captain Orton.
我的事你尽管放心好了，船长
Sometimes I wonder if you know what
you're really facing.
我当然担心，一个英国女人
独自来到这个国家
An Englishwoman alone in a country like Siam.
没关系，船长,我来这是工作的
It doesn't matter, captain.
I shall have work to do,
再说国王又答应给
我和孩子提供住所
and the king has promised me
a house of my own.
如果亡夫地下有知的话,一定会赞成的
I'll have a place to bring up my boy
as his father would have wished.
妈妈,你看,那位大臣竟然是赤裸的
Mother, look. The prime minister is naked!
别好笑了，路易,怎么可能了
Oh, don't be ridiculous, Louis.
He can't be naked.
他只是.
He's only...
...半裸的
...half-naked.
他们看起来有点吓人，妈妈
They look so cruel, Mother.
爸爸不愿意看到我们害怕，是吗？
Father wouldn't have liked us to be afraid, would he?
路易，爸爸从来不愿看到我们害怕
No, Louis. Father would not have
liked us to be afraid.
从来不
Not ever.
妈妈，你什么都不怕吗
Doesn't anything ever frighten you?
有时会的
Oh, yes, sometimes.
你害怕的时候怎么办？
我会吹口哨
- What do you do?
- I whistle.
那就是为什么你会吹口哨了
Oh, that's why you whistle.
那就是我吹口哨的原因
That's why I whistle.
当我感到害怕时
Whenever I feel afraid
我就会挺起胸膛
I hold my head erect
吹起高兴的乐曲，所以没人怀疑
And whistle a happy tune,
So no one will suspect
我害怕
I'm afraid
当我打颤时
While shivering in my shoes
我就做个无畏的动作
I strike a careless pose
吹高兴的乐曲
And whistle a happy tune
没人知道我害怕
And no one ever knows I'm afraid
口哨是很不可思议
The result of this deception
的魔法
is very strange to tell
连恐惧的对象
For when I fool the people I fear
以及自己都被蒙骗
I fool myself as well!
只要吹吹口哨
I whistle a happy tune
在短时间内
And every single time
就会被活泼的旋律
The happiness in the tune
把恐惧冲散
Convinces me that I'm not afraid.
要相信你很勇敢
Make believe you're brave
这样勇气就会充满心胸
And the trick will take you far.
你要勇敢
You may be as brave
相信你能行
As you make believe you are.
相信自己
You may be as brave
你很勇敢
As you make believe you are.
这是个好主意，妈妈，太好了
I think that's a very good idea,
Mother. A very good idea.
对，这的确是个好主意
Yes, it is a good idea, isn't it?
我不会再感到恐惧了，不会了，妈妈
I don't think I shall ever be afraid again.
这就对了
Good.
口哨是非常不可思议
The result of this deception
的魔法
ls very strange to tell
连恐惧的对象及自己
For when I fool the people I fear
都会被蒙骗
I fool myself as well!
这位是安娜李恩诺太太
This is Anna Halloweens.
李恩诺太太，他是克拉拉贺首相
Mrs. Halloweens, may I present
His Excellency, the kralahome.
请问阁下是皇室特聘的家庭教师吗
Sir, you are lady who will be
schoolmistress of the royal children?
是的
他称你阁下
- Yes.
- He called you "sir."
嘘，别说话
Hush, dear, hush.
您在曼谷有朋友吗？
Have you friends in Bangkok?
我不认识任何人
I know no one in Bangkok at all.
首相问您结婚了没有
His Excellency wishes to know,
are you married, sir?
我是个寡妇
I am a widow.
您丈夫生前的
工作是什么呢
What manner of man,
your deceased husband?
先夫是英国皇家陆军军官…
My husband was an officer
of Her Majesty's Army in...
我想问一下，
那些事…
Tell your master his business with me
跟我当家庭教师有什么关系吗
is as schoolteacher to the royal children.
我希望不要探索我的隐私
He has no right to pry
into my personal affairs.
他不是这个意思，船长
He hasn't, Captain Orton.
我不喜欢这个人
I don't like that man.
你在这的期间最好别独树一帜，明白吗？
In foreign country is best
you like everyone until you leave.
你会说英语，竟然说不会
You might at least have told us
you speak English, Your Excellency.
我不许家庭教师什么都知道
It is not necessary for schoolteacher
to know everything at once.
你现在跟我来
You come with me now.
行李待会儿运到皇宫去
Your baggages shall be carried
to palace later.
请等一下，我并不住在那
Just a minute. Not the palace.
I am not living in the palace.
谁说的
国王
- Who say?
- The king say... Says.
在他的信里答应每月给我20磅的薪水
In his letter of agreement,
he promised me 20￡ a month
并在皇宫外给我安排了住的地方
and a house of my own
outside the palace walls.
国王已经不记得他的承诺了
King do not always remember
what he promise.
那就请你提醒他好了
Then you will have to remind him.
我若提醒.会引起他的圣怒
If I tell king he break this promise,
I will make anger in him.
我不想为了这些无聊的事引起不快
I think is better if king's anger
reserved for more important matters.
好啊，如果你不敢告诉他的话
Very well, then. If you are
afraid to tell him, I will.
我是不是要见他，要视情况而定了
I should like to see him at once,
while there's time for me
或许我应该立刻返回英国
to return to England on this boat.
国王正忙呢
阁下
- King very busy now.
- Your Excellency,
我并不想占用他很多时间
all I want is
a few minutes' audience with him.
我来这是工作的，但也不会放弃自己的权利
I have come here to work
and I intend to work,
我要争取得到我应得的一切
but I shall take nothing less
than I have been promised.
你就这样对国王说话吗？
You will tell king this?
我会的
I will tell king this.
这将是一场有趣的晋见
It should be very interesting meeting.
来吧
You come now!
如果你改变主意
If you change your mind...
再见，船长，谢谢你的照顾
Goodbye, Captain Orton,
and thank you for everything.
祝你好运，夫人
Good luck, ma'am.
再见，船长
再见孩子
- Goodbye, captain.
- Goodbye, laddie.
要好好照顾你的妈妈
Take good care of your mother, now.
国王今天心情不好
King in bad spirit today.
还是改天再来吧
Suggest schoolteacher wait for better day.
我也一样心情不好，先生
My spirit is just as bad, Your Excellency.
I cannot wait.
那个男的是缅甸皇室的使者
Man is Lun Tha,
emissary from court of Burma.
那个女的是缅甸皇太子送来的礼物
He bring present to king
from prince of Burma.
她名字叫达布提
Her name is Tuptim.
那个女孩是供品
Why, that girl is a present?
送给国王的
For king.
国王收下她了
King is pleased with her.
对不起，
国王上朝的时间到此结束
Sorry. King has concluded audience.
你是说我无法晋见国王
Well, you mean I cannot see him?
下次吧
Not today.
路易，跟我来
Louis, come with me.
你不能这样
You cannot do this!
国王陛下
你是谁
- Your Majesty.
- Who, who, who?
他是请来教英语的家庭教师
Your Majesty, is new English schoolteacher.
安娜女士和她的儿子
Mrs. Anna Halloweens and son.
他叫路易
Louis Halloweens.
你是家庭教师
You are schoolteacher?
是的，陛下，但在工作之前
我要弄清楚一件事
Yes, Your Majesty. But before I start
my work here, there is one point...
我是为了让泰国更现代化…
You are part of general plan I have
for bringing to Siam
所以才找你来
what is good in Western culture.
而且我还引进了印刷机
Already I have bring printing press here
for printing.
我知道，陛下
你怎么知道的
- Yes, I know, Your Majesty.
- How you know?
在签约之前，我已经将所有的事情都调查过了
Before I signed our agreement, I found out
about your ambitions for Siam.
你有多大？
How old shall you be?
你有自信教科学方面的知识吗
You do not look like
scientific person for teaching.
你到底几岁了
How old shall you be?
我有150岁，陛下
I am 150 years old, Your Majesty.
你是哪年生的
In what year were you borned?
我是1712年
In 1712, Your Majesty.
你结婚多久了
How many years
shall you have been married?
有几年了
Several, Your Majesty.
你有多少孙子
How many grandchildren
shall you have by now?
告诉我，有多少，
有多少
How many, how many, how many?
你答不出来了吧
You do not answer fast.
我赢了，我赢了
I make better question
than she make answer.
你不怕国王
You are not afraid of king.
对，科学精神是不允许有恐惧感的
Not to be afraid is good thing
in scientific mind.
我想也许.
I think maybe
你能够当个好老师
you make very good schoolteaching.
来吧
Come.
他们都是我的妃子
A few of my wives.
他们都很美丽却没有学识
They have beauty
but not gift for knowledge.
我因为外交事务繁忙，所以没时间管教育
I have no time for teaching,
being busy with foreign affairs
和一些其他的事情
and other situations.
她是张妃，是这里的大太太
I may present Lady Thiang, head wife.
遥远的地方有个富裕的国度
There is a happy land
far, far away
到处充满了圣者的
Where saints in glory stand
耀眼国度
Bright, bright as day.
"最初是神创造了天与地"
"In the beginning, God
created the heaven and the earth."
是传教士教我的
Missionary.
传教士教你英语了
Oh, a missionary taught you English.
是的
Yes, sir. Missionary.
我也有儿子
跟他差不多大
I have boy too.
他的名字是裘雷达汗皇太子
Crown Prince Chowfa Chulalongkorn,
heir to throne.
你来当她的助手…
You help Madam Halloweens
with schoolteaching
而且要好好的学习英语
and she in turn shall teach you
the better English.
她很感谢我的仁慈安排
She is very grateful to me for my kindness.
张妃，你去带孩子们，来见见老师
Lady Thiang, have children prepare
for presentation to schoolteacher.
这个，陛下，我想先谈谈和约问题
Speaking of teaching, Your Majesty,
in our agreement...
孙妃，达拉妃，碧亚妃
Lady Son Klin, Lady Talap, Lady Piam.
而这位女孩是由缅甸送来的
And this girl is present to me
from a Burma prince.
刚刚送来
She just arrived.
你好，夫人
Good day, madam.
我叫达布提，我也会说英语
My name is Tuptim. I already speak English.
你说的非常好
And very nicely too.
我有个更好的主意
I think I have fine idea.
在教孩子之余，顺便教教这些妃子们
In addition to children, you will also teach
those of my wives
教她们…科学知识
as have sense enough for learning.
先进国家的女性
Siam to be very modern, scientific country.
都会说英语
Everybody speaking the English.
但是国王陛下，我记得契约上没写要教妃子
Your Majesty, it is not in our agreement
that I teach your wives too.
另外你可以帮我写写外交文件
Also, I will allow you to help me
in my foreign correspondence.
我很乐意为你效劳
I shall be perfectly happy to help you
in any way I can
但是我想先谈谈房子的事情
provided we can clear up
this one little matter of the house.
房子？
House?
房子？什么房子
House? What house?
我记得你答应在皇宫旁边盖间房子给我的
My house, Your Majesty. The one
you promised me, adjoining the palace.
最好是住在皇宫里
It is a pleasure that you
shall live in palace.
在皇宫里教书，你就住在这
You teach in palace,
and you shall live in palace.
从这里可以看到很多美丽的景色
Will have nice apartment.
Can look out, see many things.
我当然知道看到什么东西了
Oh, yes, I'm sure we could see many things,
那就是铁栏杆，卫兵，等等等等
such as iron bars, guards at the doors,
et cetera, et cetera.
什么是等等
What is this "et cetera"?
那是表示还有其他相似东西的意思
Well, it means "and all the rest
and so forth," Your Majesty.
来见见我的孩子们
You will meet my children.
国王陛下，如果房子的问题没谈妥的话
I'm sorry, Your Majesty,
but if there is to be no house,
我想搭原来的船返回英国
I shall have to get back to the boat.
别再说了，见见我的孩子们
You will stand here and meet royal children.
遵命，陛下
Very well, Your Majesty.
但请快点
But there isn't much time.
王子和公主进来吧
The royal princes and princesses.
来
Well, well, well?
现在你还要解决房子的问题
Schoolteacher has graciously
changed her mind and shall live in palace.
房子迟些再说，陛下
For the time being, Your Majesty.
这些都是你要教的
These are the children you shall teach.
改天我让你见见其他的孩子
Someday shall allow you
to meet my others.
还有其他的孩子？
More, Your Majesty?
还有些不住在宫里的
Children of wives not in favor with king.
一共是67个
Sixty-seven, I think.
67个
Oh.
不
Hmm.
不，别这样，别乱动行李箱
No! Oh, ladies, please. Don't open that, no.
哦，我的天，请回你们自己房间去
Oh, my goodness! Oh, won't you all
go back to your rooms?
张妃，请叫她们别这样
Lady Thiang, will you please
ask them to leave?
我有自己的隐私
I must have some privacy.
天哪，她们到底想干什么
Good heavens!
What are they trying to do to me?
他们想知道你的身体是否也像裙子的形状
Sir, they think you wear dress like that
because you shaped like that.
哦，当然不是
Well, I most certainly am not.
他们只是想了解，阁下
你的孩子呢，他在哪
They wish to know, sir,
if they may see the boy?
对不起，他正在睡觉
I'm sorry, Lady Thiang, he is asleep.
请告诉我为什么称我为阁下
Please, do tell me.
Why do you keep calling me sir?
因为你不是普通的女人
Because you scientific,
not lowly like woman.
难道女人比男人低一等吗
But do you all think
that women are more lowly than men?
那是非常错误的观点
Well, I certainly do not.
要是让国王听到了会大发雷霆的
Please, sir, do not tell king.
Make king angry.
国王陛下也需要接受教育才行
Perhaps it's time somebody did tell him
a thing or two.
安娜夫人
Mrs. Anna?
请问你有没有英文书借给我看
Please, you have some English books
I can read?
当然有,可是要等到行李箱打开才行
Yes, of course, my dear,
but they're not unpacked yet.
她们笑她是因为她很愚蠢
They laugh at her
because she is foolish child.
她能在皇宫伺候国王，但并不快乐
She has come to live in palace of king
and yet she is unhappy.
毕竟，她在这件事上别无选择
After all, she had no choice in the matter.
我想她一定是思念自己的故乡
Perhaps she is homesick.
不是思念故乡
Is not homesickness that make me sad,
Mrs. Anna.
而是思念我无法再见到的人
Is love for one I shall never see again.
哦，可怜的孩子
Oh, poor child.
他就是带我来的使者伦塔
He is Lun Tha,
who was chosen to bring me here.
我们都极力克制过了…
We tried so hard
not to have love for each other
但还是情不自禁的双双堕入了情网
but we could not help ourselves.
我们试过了
We did try, Mrs. Anna.
思念不是说停就能停下来的
It isn't easy to stop loving a man
if he's the man you want.
并不是不见就能割断思念之情
Even if you know
you will never see him again.
我知道
I know.
我也非常思念我的先夫
I was very much in love with my husband.
请你们放回原处好吗
Please ask them to put that down.
大家想知道他是谁
They wish to know, sir, who is man?
他就是我死去的丈夫汤姆
That was my husband, Tom.
汤姆
- Tom.
- Mm-hmm.
他长的很帅
He was pretty in face.
是啊，他长的非常英俊
Oh, dear, yes, he was. Very pretty in face.
每当我想起他
When I think of Tom
就禁不住想那一夜
I think about a night
大地弥漫着夏日的气息
When the earth smelled of summer
云朵在天空漂浮
And the sky was streaked with white
轻柔的雾气弥漫
And the soft mist of England
着英格兰小山冈
Was sleeping on a hill,
这些我都记得
I remember this
永远记得
And I always will.
我深知我俩的爱情
There are new lovers now
见证在寂静山岗
On the same silent hill
常常浮现在我的脑海
Looking on the same blue sea,
汤姆和我永远
And I know Tom and I
是大地的一分子
are a part of them all,
而他们也是汤姆的一分子
And they're all a part of Tom
我也是
and me.
年轻的爱人们，无论你是谁
Hello, young lovers, whoever you are,
希望你们一切顺利
I hope your troubles are few.
我的祝愿伴你度过今宵
All my good wishes go with you tonight.
我也像你们一样爱过
I've been in love like you.
提起勇气
Be brave, young lovers,
抓住幸运之星
and follow your star,
提起勇气抓住真爱
Be brave and faithful and true,
紧紧相拥
Cling very close
在日升之前
to each other tonight.
我也像你们一样爱过
I've been in love like you.
我知道脚上长翅膀
是什么样的感觉
I know how it feels
to have wings on your heels
在梦中徘徊散步
And to fly down a street in a trance.
你们相识在偶然
You fly down a street
on the chance that you'll meet,
你们相识
And you meet
真的不是意外
not really by chance.
无论你们做了什么，
年轻的爱人们，别哭
Don't cw, young lovers whatever you do
别因为我孤独而为我哭泣
Don't cry because I'm alone,
我所有的记忆让我
All of my mem'ries
今晚很快乐
are happy tonight,
我曾经有过自己的爱
I've had a love of my own,
像你们一样
like yours,
我曾经有过
I've had a love
自己的爱
of my own.
快乐的殿堂
Be it pleasures and palaces,
任我们遨游
Though we may roam,
曾经如此卑微
Be it ever so humble,
如家般温暖
There's no place like home.
天空的魅力
A charm from the skies
我们共同分享
Seems to hallow us there,
父皇，我上学快迟到了
- Father, I'll be late for school!
- You wait.
你昨天在学校学过什么谚语…
You are pleased to recite proverb
you learn yesterday
应该写过十二遍了吧
and writing down 12 times in copybook.
"不管在东方--
"A thought for the day:
还是西方"
East or west,
没有比家更舒适之处"
home is best."
东方、西方、家，又提到了房子
"East, west, home, best," means house!
"房子仅次于名誉…"
"A man's house is only less dear to him
than his honor."
每天总是提到房子的事
Every day, month after week,
something about house.
除了房子你还学到别的事吗
Are my children to be taught nothing more?
昨天她说…
Yesterday we are taught
地球像球一样的圆
that the world is a round ball
还会旋转呢…
which spins on an invisible stick
through its middle.
可是，地球应该在龟背上才对
Everyone knows
the world rides on the back of a turtle
这样才会安全
who keeps it from running into the stars.
但是接受己见不一定是对的…
How can it be
that everyone knows one thing
顽固的人总是犯下错？
if many people believe another thing?
那真相是什么呢
Then which is true?
我相信地球应该是…
The world is ball
圆的并且会旋转
with stick through it.
我相信
I believe.
你相信？
You believe?
所以你无所不知才行
Does that mean that you do not know?
没错，你必须知道，因为你要成为国王
But you must know, because you are king.
没错
Good.
有天你也会当上国王的
Someday you too will be king,
那时你就知道所有的事
and you too will know everything.
我怎么才能学习到呢
But how do I learn?
怎样才能无所不知呢
And when do I know that I know everything?
当你成为国王的时候
When you are king.
可我不知道
But I do not know.
我没有一件事确定…
In my head are many facts,
but I am not sure.
我该如何告诉她.
What to tell a growing son?
如何正确对待政治和子民呢
How to bring truth and justice
to my people?
当我是个孩子时
When I was a boy,
世界比现在还灿烂
World was better spot,
什么都是
What was so was so,
黑白分明
What was not was not.
现在我长大了
Now I am a man,
万事都改变了
World have change a lot
有些事很像
Some things nearly so,
有些事又不像
Others nearly not.
有时我又不确定
There are times I almost think
什么事我绝对知道
I am not sure of what I absolutely know;
不再有了
Very often find confusion
以往的结论
In conclusion I concluded long ago.
我头脑里有很多东西
In my head are many facts that,
当学生时学的东西
As a student I have studied to procure
我头脑里有很多东西
In my head are many facts,
我希望能有把握一点
Of which I wish I was more certain
我知道
I was sure.
这是个问题
Is a puzzlement.
我要跟其他的国家联合吗？
Shall I join with other nations in alliance?
如果联合失败了
我就失去了威信
If allies are weak am I not best alone?
如果联合成功了
If allies are strong with power
to protect me,
借着权力可以保护自己
Might they not protect me out of all I own?
也许他们不会保护我
Is a danger to be trusting one another,
相信别人是危险的
One will seldom want to do
what other wishes;
但人们永远无法彼此信任
But unless someday,
Somebody trust somebody,
除非有天都彼此相信了
There'll be nothing left on earth
地球上除了鱼什么也不剩
excepting fishes!
有段时间我想没人可信
There are times I almost think
也没人绝对知道什么
nobody sure of what he absolutely know,
人们为以往下的结论
everybody find confusion
困惑不已
In conclusion he concluded long ago.
有时人们会满腹牢骚
And it puzzle me to learn
有时人们又会刮目相看
that tho' a man may be in doubt
of what he know,
他们的斗争非常快
Very quickly will he fight,
他们斗争是想证明
He'll fight to prove
that what he does not know
他不知道又怎么样
is so.
哦
Ohhhh!
有时我以为人民发疯了
Sometimes I think that people going mad!
啊
Ahhhh!
有时觉得他们没这么坏
Sometimes I think that people not so bad.
可无论我想什么
But no matter what I think,
我不能放弃国王的职责
I must go on living life.
As leader of my kingdom
我必须尽到
I must go forth,
父亲对孩子丈夫对妻子的职责
Be father to my children,
And husband to each wife,
等等等等
Et cetera, et cetera, and so forth.
请指给我一个明示之道
If my Lord in heaven
Buddha show the way,
我一直在努力
Ev'ry day I try to live another day,
请指给我一个明示之道
If my Lord in heaven
Buddha show the way,
每天我都在努力
Ev'ry day I do my best for one more day,
可是
But
那是多么难啊
is a puzzlement
好了，孩子们，我们开始上课了
Come along now, children.
Take your places, please.
请你们快点，不要说话
Quickly now, and quietly.
张妃，你开始上课
Lady Thiang,
will you start the lesson, please?
蓝色的部分
Blue
是海洋
is ocean.
红色的部分是
Red,
泰国
Siam.
这是泰国的国王
Here is king of Siam.
右手上拿着是
In right hand is weapon.
消灭敌人的
Show how he destroy
武器
all who fight him.
绿色部分是
Green,
缅甸
Burma.
这是缅甸国王
Here is king of Burma.
他光着身子
No clothes mean
因为缅甸太穷没有衣服穿
how poor is king of Burma.
谢谢你的解释张妃
Thank you, Lady Thiang. I'll continue.
这张地图是25年前的了…
The map you have been looking at
is 25 years old,
今天我们要看新的地图
and today we have a surprise for you.
这是刚刚从英国送来的地图
A new map just arrived from England.
我都找不到泰国
I do not see Siam.
这个白色的地方就是
The white is Siam.
泰国这么小
Siam not so small.
看，英国在这
Well, wait. Let me show you England.
看到了吗？它比泰国还小呢
See? It is even smaller than Siam.
以前对我来说
泰国只是地图上的小白点
Before I came here,
Siam was just that little white spot to me.
但是到这几个月后，已经不是
我想象的那个样子了
Now that I've been here many months
it has become far more than that
因为我现在已经喜欢上了这个国家
because I've met the people of Siam,
and I'm learning to understand them.
你喜欢我们吗
You like us, Mrs. Anna?
是的，我很喜欢
Yes, I like you very much.
非常喜欢
Very much, indeed.
有句很古老的谚语
It's a very ancient saying,
现在能表达我的心情
But a true and honest thought,
如果你们当了老师
That if you become a teacher,
教你们的学生
By your pupils you'll be taught,
作为老师我也在学习
As a teacher I've been learning
如果我有不对请原谅我
And I've now become an expert,
现在我最喜欢做的事
On the subject I like most,
了解你们
Getting to know you.
Getting to know you,
了解你们所有的人
Getting to know all about you.
喜欢你们
Getting to like you,
希望你们喜欢我
Getting to hope you like me.
越是了解你们
Getting to know you,
我就越喜欢你们
Putting it my way,
越是喜欢
but nicely,
你们就象是我
You are precisely
杯中的茶
My Cup of tea!
越是了解你们
Getting to know you,
越感觉轻松自在
Getting to feel free and easy.
当我跟你们在一起时
When I am with you,
我就想说话
Getting to know what to say,
你们没注意到吗？
Haven't you noticed?
我突然感到欢快轻松
Suddenly I'm bright and breezy
因为我从你们身上
Because of all the beautiful and new things
学到了很多美丽的东西
I'm learning about you
一起唱
day by
一起
daY-
了解你们
Getting to know you,
了解你们大家
Getting to know all about you.
逐渐喜欢上你们
Getting to like you,
希望你们也喜欢我
Getting to hope you like me.
了解你们
Getting to know you,
每天不断发现你们的魅力
Putting it my way, but nicely,
你们就象
You are precisely
我杯里的茶
My Cup of tea!
越了解你们
Getting to know you,
我越感到轻松自在
Getting to feel free and easy.
当我跟你们在一起时
When I am with you,
我就想说话
Getting to know what to say,
你们没注意到吗
Haven't you noticed?
我突然感到欢快轻松
Suddenly I'm bright and breezy
因为我从你们的身上学到了
Because of all the beautiful and new things
很多美丽的东西
I'm learning about you
一起唱
day by
一起
daY-
本版本字幕由 Wendy's PaPa 翻译、整理、调校时间轴
This version subtitles by Wendy's PaPa
越了解你们
Getting to know you,
我越感到轻松自在
Getting to feel free and easy.
当我跟你们在一起时
When I am with you,
我就想说话
Getting to know what to say,
你们没注意到吗
Haven't you noticed?
Suddenly I'm bright and breezy
因为我从你们
的身上学到了
Because of all the beautiful and new things
很多美丽的东西
I'm learning about you
一起唱
day by
一起
daY
越了解你们
Getting to know you,
我越感到轻松自在
Getting to feel free and easy.
当我跟你们在一起时
When I am with you,
我就想说话
Getting to know what to say,
你们没注意到吗
Haven't you noticed?
Suddenly I'm bright and breezy
因为我从你们的身上学到了
Because of all the beautiful and new things
很多美丽的东西
I'm learning about you
一起唱
daY
一起
DY
来
daY-
哦，糟了，我们应上地理课
Goodness, this started out
to be a geography lesson.
快点，我们来上课
Quickly, let's get back to work.
快点
Shh! Shh! Shh!
那个绿色的是什么？
- Now...
- What is that green up there?
那是挪威
That is Norway.
挪-威
Nor... way.
挪威是个非常冷的国家
Norway is a very cold place.
有时因为太冷.
Sometimes it is so cold,
湖水和江河都结了冰…
that the lakes and rivers freeze
那时候就可以在冰上行走
and the water becomes so hard
that you can walk on it.
走在冰上
Walk on water?
是的，在冰上走
Yes, walk on water.
听上去不太可能
How is it possible?
有那么硬的水吗
Hard water?
知道吗，雨水冰冻的时候
Not only that, but the raindrops
change into small white spots
就会成为蕾丝状
that look like lace.
那就是雪
And this is called "snow."
雪
Snow.
蕾丝状
Spots of lace!
是的，殿下。雨从空中降落的途中就会变成雪
Yes, Your Highness. The water freezes
on its way down from the sky.
我才不相信有雪这种东西
I do not believe such thing as snow.
我也不相信有雪
And I do not believe such thing as snow.
我不相信泰国有这么小…
And I do not believe Siam is this big.
外国却那么大
And other country so big.
我们是世界上最大的国家
- Siam is biggest country in world!
- Siam!
什么
What, what, what?
这就是科学式的教学吗？
How can schoolroom be so unscientific?
陛下，他们不理解我在说什么
Well, Your Majesty,
we had a little misunderstanding.
我在解释什么是雪
I was trying to describe snow
他们竟然不相信有这种东西
and they refused to believe
there is such a thing.
雪？
Snow?
雪
Snow.
从山上落下来的
From mountaintop.
从天空落下，陛下
From sky, Your Majesty.
从天空落到山上然后再落下来
From sky to mountaintop.
对，陛下
That's right, Your Majesty.
我在照片里见过的
I remember. I see pictures of Switzerland.
瑞士笼罩在雪里一片洁白
Land all white with snow.
你们为什么不相信
Who does not believe this?
陛下，因为他们没有亲眼见过
Well, after all, they've never seen it.
没有见过
Never seen?
如果只相信见过的事物，就不需要学校了
If they believe only what they see,
why do we have schoolroom? Rise!
站起来，要相信老师的话…
Never let me hear
of not believing schoolteacher
她是我专程从英国请来的…
whom I have bring here at high expense.
每个月要付20磅
Twenty pounds each month.
20英镑
Twenty English pounds.
坐下
Sterling!
站起来
Rise!
这是为你们个人.
I command all of you
和国家着想…
to make most of this opportunity
for expensive education.
所以别浪费了这么贵的上课费…
For sake of selves and country.
为了自己也是为了国家
Furthermore, it is...
什么，什么，不是我给你的书吧
What, what, what?
This is not study book I have provide.
不，陛下，是我的书
No, Your Majesty, it's one of mine.
我给她的
那本书是叫什么
- I gave it to Tuptim.
- The name! You tell me!
是汤姆叔叔的小屋
Is calledThe Small House of Uncle Thomas.
作者是美国的斯陀夫人
ls by American lady, Harriet Beecher Stowe.
一个女人也可以写书？
A woman has written a book?
汤姆叔叔的小屋，是本很优秀的作品
Uncle Tom's Cabin.
A wonderful book, Your Majesty.
是批评美奴隶制的
All about the evils of slavery in America.
林肯先生也是反对派的
President Lincoln of America
against slavery, no?
没错，陛下
Very definitely, Your Majesty.
我也不喜欢
Me too.
奴隶制很不好
Slavery very bad thing.
林肯为了解放奴隶而战，仍被人们喝彩
Mr. Lincoln is fighting a war,
even now, to set the slaves free.
你认为他很了不起
You admire him for this?
是的，陛下
Very much, Your Majesty.
他不怕吃苦.
He seems to be a fine man
who has studied hard
独自学习
and educated himself.
这点您就比他差点了
In that, he is not unlike yourself.
你认为他打赢之后赢得了总统的职位？
Shall Mr. Lincoln be winning this war
he is fighting at present?
我不这么认为
No one knows, really.
他有足够的枪和大象来运输
Does he have enough guns and elephants
for transporting same?
在美国是没有大象的，陛下
I don't think they have elephants
in America, Your Majesty.
没有大象？没有
- No elephants?
- No.
那他一定输定了
No wonder he's not winning war.
好了，孩子们，该上课了
All right, children, you may be seated now.
安娜夫人
什么事，裘雷拉汗
- Mrs. Anna?
- Yes, Your Highness?
我不明白
I do not understand
当主人解放奴隶之后…那些奴隶该怎么办呢
how slaves can be set free
if their masters wish to keep them.
必要时要执行法律
It's done by the passing of a law
强制性执行
and by the enforcing of that law,
if necessary.
但是如果我有奴隶
But my slaves
或者是父皇有奴隶…
and the slaves of my father...
而我们又反对这种法律该怎么办呢
Suppose there was such a law in Siam
and we did not want it so?
有时应该抑制欲望选择正确的
Sometimes things can't be just
a question of what we want, Highness,
这才是真正的为王之道
but of what is right.
对的
Ha.
好了，现在你们可以休息吃午饭了
I think perhaps we had better call
recess until after luncheon.
你们可以回去
You may be excused.
年轻的皇太子会
Young prince has healthy respect
更认真地考虑人民的事
for ways of his own people.
有时甚至会超过国王
Sometimes more than king.
他是位思想很细致
Prince Chulalongkorn is a fine boy
with a keen and probing mind.
有强烈探索心的孩子
But he still has much to learn,
Your Excellency.
今后的教育，对他有重要的作用.
What is important for him to learn
不，我不认为这个教室对他有作用
I do not think he'll find
in this classroom.
这么说你是反对我来这教书了
I'm fully aware that you do not
approve of my coming to Siam.
你怎么看不出来呢
Why are you so blind?
Have you no eyes to see?
国王是向不可能挑战
King tries impossible task
讲究科学，讲究现代化
wishing to be scientific man
who learn all modern things.
我认为他有崇高的理想
I think it a fine ambition.
继承了父王的强大意志，不可能轻易改变
Inside him is strong king like
his father, who cannot change.
如果过于勉强导致灭亡
He will only tear himself in two, trying
to be something he can never be.
就得不偿失了
Of course he can never be
当然他需要身边的人协助,你说不是吗
if those closest to him
are unwilling to help him.
你根本不之道国王在想什么,你又能做些什么
You do not know king
as well as you think you do.
你永远相信你有过人的智慧
You believe you have
great influence over him.
反正你也会成为国王的奴隶
You will end up as his slave
like all the others.
我…
I...
来了，请等一下
Yes, yes. Just a moment.
国王？
The king?
在这个时候
At this hour of the night?
好，那就先等我换件衣服吧
Well, I trust His Majesty won't object
if I put some clothes on first.
你召我来吗，陛下
You sent for me, Your Majesty?
陛下
Your Majesty.
原来陛下在看圣经
Oh, Your Majesty is reading
the Bible.
安娜夫人
Mrs. Anna,
我觉得摩西这个人实在是笨极了
I think your Moses
shall have been a fool.
摩西？
Moses?
摩西，摩西，摩西
我认为他是个大傻瓜
Moses, Moses, Moses.
I think he shall have been a fool.
他说.
Here it stands written by him
世界是在六天内造成的简直是开玩笑
that the world was created
in six days.
我们都知道…
Now you know and I know
这是经过几百万年演化而成的
that it took many ages
to create world.
他真是个没知识的人才这么写
I think he shall have been a fool
to have written so.
你看呢
What is your opinion?
国王陛下半夜三更的把我叫来，就是为了这件事
Is that why Your Majesty sent for me
at this hour of the night?
没理由，在讲重要事之前，还是先谈摩西
That is not reason, but first
I wish to discuss Moses.
你去哪寻求真实呢
Now, how am I ever to learn truth
如果每本书上写的都不一样的话
if different English books
state different things?
圣经不是一本科学化的书,是由信仰完成的
The Bible was not written by men
of science, but by men of faith.
他们只是在颂扬神创造的奇迹
It was their explanation
of the miracle of creation,
问题不在于几天还是几个世纪造成的
which is the same miracle whether
it took six days or many centuries.
我还是认为摩西是个大笨蛋
I still think your Moses
shall have been a fool.
你高兴怎么认为就怎么认为好了
As you wish, Your Majesty.
请问还有别的事吗
Now, was there something else?
写信
Take letter.
写信？ 现在？
A letter? Now?
现在写，现在的事情现在就做
Now. When else?
Now is always best time.
我要寄给有科学精神的林肯先生
Take letter to Mr. Lincoln of America,
who is very scientific ruler.
好吧，陛下
Very well, Your Majesty.
"受全宇宙…
From Phra Mama Mongut,
"最高权利祝福的…
by the blessing of the highest
super agency in the world
"泰国国王，君临天下
of the whole universe,
the king of Siam.
"领属至尊，高贵无比，拥有至高无上的权力
Sovereign of all tributary countries
adjacent and in every direction,
等等，等等"
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
你不尊敬国王吗
Do you not have any respect for me?
为什么你站着比我的头还高呢
Why do you stand over my head?
任何时间都不许站在我面前
I cannot stand all the time.
在这个国家，是不允许低头看国王的
And in this country no one's head
shall be higher than king's.
你必须像我其他的臣下一样…
From now on in presence, you shall
so conduct like all other subjects.
你是要我趴在地上
You mean, on the floor?
所有的人都是这么做的
All subjects do so.
非常抱歉，陛下
I'm very sorry.
我最多只能把头低下
I shall try my best not to let my head
be higher than Your Majesty's,
可我拒绝趴在地上
but I simply cannot
grovel on the floor.
因为那样我就无法写信了
I couldn't possibly
work that way, or think.
你是个顽固的女人.
You are very difficult woman!
也许如此，陛下
Perhaps so, Your Majesty.
总之我不许你低头看我
But observe care that head
shall not be higher than mine.
我坐下时你也得坐下，我跪下时你也得跪下…
When I shall sit, you shall sit!
When I shall kneel, you shall kneel.
等等，等等
Et cetera, et cetera, et cetera!
遵命，陛下
Very well, Your Majesty.
这算是承诺吗
Is promise?
是承诺
很好
- Is promise.
- Good.
"美利坚合众国的…
To His Royal Presidency
of the United States in America...
"亚伯拉罕，林肯先生…"
"Abrahom Lingkong"...
写个适当的称呼
...et cetera. You fix up.
"非常突然的…"
It has occurred to us...
"就是非常突然的…"
You see, it has occurred to us...
"非常突然的，让我送几头
It has occurred to us that if we
shall be sending you several pairs
"公象给你们吧…
of young male elephants
只要放到美国的大森林里
to be turned loose
in forests of America...
美国
A-mer-i-ca.
"我想.
We are of opinion
"总有一天，大象的数量是会增多的
that after a while
they shall increase in number.
会越来越多'
陛下…
- And inhabitants of America shall...
- Your Majesty.
什么事
Well?
你不是说只送公象吗
I don't think you mean pairs
of male elephants.
你不要插嘴行吗？
How can I make letter if you interrupt?
"这样一来.就可以加紧驯服.
And inhabitants of America shall be
able to catch and tame them
利用他们搬运货物"
and use them as beasts of burden.
只有公象吗，陛下？
Only male elephants, Your Majesty?
你可以写的更加详细点
You put in the details.
晚安
Good night.
摩西
Moses.
林肯
Lincoln!
大象
Elephants!
半夜叫我趴在地上
Groveling on the floor
at 2:00 in the morning.
夫人，我是伦塔
I am Lun Tha.
你是家庭教师安娜夫人吗
You are Mrs. Anna, schoolteacher?
是的，可这禁止男人进入
Yes, but you shouldn't be...
我非常想见达布提求求你了
I must meet with Tuptim again.
Please!
你们以前在这见过面？
You have been seeing her here?
见过两次
Twice we have spoken.
但戒备森严
Each time it becomes more difficult.
她说过，你可以帮我们
She has said you will help us.
不，不行
Oh, no, I couldn't!
那样做太危险了
It's much too dangerous.
我很为你们的安全担心
Not for me, but for Tuptim and you.
在男人的禁地如被发现就活不了了，马上离开
You'll be killed if they find you in
the City of Women. You must leave!
与其痛苦的活着,还不如死了算了
求你了，安娜夫人
Death is not worse pain than
empty life. Please, Mrs. Anna.
抱歉
I'm sorry, Lun Tha.
我不能帮你的忙
There's nothing I can do.
你等着
Wait there.
达布提
Tuptim.
伦塔
Oh, Lun Tha.
我已经无法再忍耐
Seeing you this way is not enough.
但是我们又能怎么样呢
There is nothing we can do.
随时都有人监视着我
I am watched too closely.
难道我们要永远这样下去吗
Must we go on forever
hiding our love like this?
在黑暗中拥吻
We kiss in a shadow
避开明亮的月光
We hide from the moon,
相逢之期渺茫
Our meetings are few
时光飞逝
and over too soon.
我们耳语
We speak in a whisper,
害怕被偷听
Afraid to be heard;
害怕见到人影
When people are near,
不敢说话
We speak not a word.
一些其他的事情
Alone in our secret,
保守着我们的秘密
Together we sigh
等待
for one smiling day
我们相逢的那天
to be free,
为了在阳光下亲吻
To kiss in the sunlight,
以响彻云霄的声音呐喊
And say to the sky:
"相信我们的爱"
Behold and believe
永远相信
what you see!
'爱我"
Behold
我爱的人
how my lover
爱我
loves me!
什么时候我们才能成为那样呢？
When will we be together, Tuptim?
什么时候？
When?
恐怕永远都无法实现…
It can never be, Lun Tha.
永远不会
Not ever.
在阳光下拥吻
To kiss in the sunlight
以响彻云霄的声音呐喊
And say to the sky:
"相信我们的爱"
Behold and believe
永远相信
What you see!
爱我
Behold
我爱的人
how my lover
"爱我"
loves me!
你得走了
You must go now.
我再不回去就要被发现，那就麻烦了
I will be missed, and they will
start searching for me.
总有一天我要带你离开这的
When I return, it will be
to take you from here.
那是不可能的
There is no way, Lun Tha.
我们从河上逃走
There is a river. There are boats.
我会寻找路线的
I will find a way.
如果可能的话
Oh, if it could only be.
绝对有可能
It will be. I swear this.
等我安排好了，就来通知你
When all is arranged,I will get word to you.
我为你祈祷
I shall pray, Lun Tha.
当你再看到这种花落的时候
If you see a chaba flower in your
path, broken like this,
就是我来接你的信号，记住
it will be the sign that
I have come for you. Watch for it.
我会准备好等着你
I will be ready.
停下，停下，停下
Stop, stop, STUD!
陛下
什么事
- Your Majesty.
- What, what, what?
什么事
Well?
去年割让领土给法国
When Siam's richest province
was stolen by France,
我有不安的预感
I warned it was only
beginning of Western treachery.
再这样下去
If enemies of ours,
with lies such as this
英国也会象这样侵占我们的领土了
can convince British that you are
unfit to be ruler of Siam,
我国将会成为侵略者的食饵
our seas will soon be thick
with ships, greedy for conquest.
如果真是那样
So it has finally come.
后果将不堪设想
We must act quickly.
可我们应该怎么办
But how? Where?
这时我应该
I must think.
冷静的和科学性的思考
Clearly. Scientifically.
我必须思考
I must think.
可他们这样，我无法思考
But how can I think
while being driven out of mind!
灿烂的阳光
A charm from the skies
慈祥的抚慰着我们
Seems to hallow us there
无论我们在哪
Which seek through the world,
都会照射我们
ls ne'er met with elsewhere.
真是好极了，可以打满分
That was splendid. Very effective.
现在…
Now...
早安，陛下
你教这样的课
- Good morning.
- You think you teach king lesson!
我无法付你高薪
This is one lesson you do not
be paid for teaching!
我不允许你教我的孩子甜蜜的家这类的书
You will stop instructing wives
and children in"Home Sweet House"
你总是在提醒我，没有兑现承诺，等等
in order to remind me of breaking
promises I never make, et cetera.
陛下.我在这无法养育我的儿子
Your Majesty, I do not intend to have
my boy brought up in a harem.
你答应过在皇宫旁边给我建一座房子
You did promise me a house.
"A brick residence adjoining the palace."
你在信中答应过的
我不记得有过这种事
- Those were your very words.
- I do not remember such words!
我还记得
我记得
- I remember them.
- I will do remembering!
在这谁是国王
Who is king here?
我提醒你,我要你记住
我不记得什么承诺
I remind you so you remember that.
I do not remember any promises.
我不记得任何事,因为你是我的仆人
I do not remember anything
except that you are my servant.
不，陛下
Oh, no, Your Majesty.
什么
What, what, what?
记住，你只是我的仆人而已
I said, you are my servant!
不，陛下，不是，我不是你的仆人
No, Your Majesty, that is not true.
I am most certainly not your servant!
如果你不照约定给我房子的话…
If you do not give me
the house you promised,
我就立刻回英国去
I shall be forced
to return to England.
不，不，安娜夫人
No! No! Please, Mrs. Anna.
我们相信老师
Please. We believe schoolteacher!
我们相信有雪
I believe in snow!
请挽留她
Do not let her go away.
我绝对不允许有人反抗我
I let her do nothing
that is not my pleasure.
你必须留在这…
It is my pleasure that you stay here!
必须留在皇宫里不许；离开
In palace! In palace!
不，陛下
No, Your Majesty.
你怎么忍心丢下这些孩子不管呢
Why do you wish
to leave these children,
他们是多么的喜欢你，女教师
all of whom are loving you
so extraordinarily?
我当然不希望离开他们，我也很喜欢他们
I do not wish to leave them. I love
them too, quite extraordinarily.
可我无法留在一个不守信用的国家
I cannot stay where a promise
has no meaning.
请你说话放尊重点…
I will hear no more!
你说想要把泰国发展成为
A land where there is a wish
for Siam
一个现代的国家
to take her place
in the modern world,
你只是嘴上说说而已，实际上还是保持着旧态
but where everything still remains
according to the wishes of the king!
你应该听我的
You will say no more! No more!
我不会再说什么了，该说的我都说了
I will say no more, because
there is no more to say!
我们走，路易
Come, Louis.
退下
Out, out, out!
是谁
Who is it?
是我，张妃
Mrs. Anna, it is I, Lady Thiang.
请进来，张妃
Oh, well, come in, Lady Thiang.
安娜夫人，请立刻去向国王报道
Mrs. Anna, you must
go to king at once.
为什么要那样做呢？
Indeed? And why must I?
我的任务已经完成了,打算坐下班船回英国
I plan to leave on the next sailing.
求求你了，安娜夫人
Please, Mrs. Anna.
是他派你来说服我的
Did he send you here to ask me?
不，是我自己来的
No. It is I who ask you.
国王现在正面临困境
King is in terrible distress,
not knowing where to turn.
困境
Distress?
他得到一封新加坡寄给英国政府的信
Agents in Singapore have found copies
of letters to British government
说泰国国王是野蛮人…
which describe king as barbarian
应该归英国管才对
and suggest necessity
of making Siam a protectorate.
哦，怎么能那样
Oh, but that is outrageous!
虽然国王有很多缺点,可他并不是野蛮人
The king is many things I dislike,
but he is not a barbarian.
你答应帮他了？
Then you will go to him now?
你是要我提供意见给他
You mean, to advise him?
不是建议
It must not sound like advice.
国王不需要任何意见
King cannot take advice.
你自己向他提出这件事
And he will not bring up subject.
You must do it for him.
不行，张妃,我也有自己的立场
No, Lady Thiang, I can't.
It's against all my principles.
他需要帮助，安娜夫人
He needs help, Mrs. Anna.
你可以帮他
Oh, but he has you.
我无法胜任这个重任
I am not equal to his special needs.
不行，张妃
Please, Lady Thiang, I simply cannot
go to him, especially without
何况他本人没有求我
his having asked for me.
你还要我说什么呢？
What more can I say to you?
他是个很用心思考的人
This is a man
who thinks with his heart,
虽然有时欠缺思考
His heart is not always wise.
即使绊倒了
This is a man who stumbles and falls.
也会再试的
But this is a man who tries.
请原谅他的过错
This is a man you'll forgive and forgive,
帮帮他
and help and protect,
只要你活着
as long as you live.
他就不会说
He will not always say
即使他没有遵守承诺
What you would have him say,
可他会说些别的
But now and then he'll say
来讨你的欢心
something wonderful.
让你忘掉不快
The thoughtless things he'll do
忘掉对你的伤害
will hurt and worry you.
他会做的很好
Then all at once he'll do
他有几千个
something wonderful.
无法实现的梦
He has a thousand dreams
你知道
that won't come true,
他很相信他们
You know that he believes in them,
那样对你够了
And that's enough
如果他错了
for you
有你在他身后
You'll always go along,
告诉他错了
Defend him when he's wrong,
当需要时提醒他
And tell him when he's strong,
他会很出色的
He is wonderful.
他一直需要你的爱
He'll always need your love,
他要得到你的爱
And so he'll get your love.
一个需要你爱的男人
A man who needs your love
会的
can be
会很出色
wonderful.
陛下
Your Majesty.
你是来道歉的
You have come to apologize.
对不起，陛下--
这样就足够了
- I am sorry, Your Majesty, but...
- Good! You apologize.
我并没有说-
我原谅你了
- I didn't say...
- I accept.
谢谢你.陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
是吗？
Well?
如你所见，我正在想一些事情
Do you not see I am occupied?
考虑一些重要的问题
My mind on very important matters.
有什么事情愿意告诉我吗？
Anything you wish to discuss with me?
我是不会对女人谈政治的？
Why should I discuss important matter with woman?
很好，陛下，那么晚安了
Very well, Your Majesty. In that case
I shall say good night.
晚安！
Good night!
陛下
Your Majesty...
什么事？什么事？什么事？
我很好奇
- What, what, what?
- I wonder...
今天有艘船从新加坡来--
新加坡，是的
- When the boat came from Singapore...
- Singapore!
带来什么消息吗？
消息！
- Was there any news from abroad?
- News!
当然有了
There were news!
他们居然说我是野蛮人！
谁？
- They call me barbarian.
- Who?
他们正想利用这个籍口来侵略我们
Parties who would use this
as excuse to steal my country.
如果你是英国女王的话…
Now suppose
you are Queen Victoria,
有人说泰国是个野蛮的国家，你会信么？
and someone say to you king of Siam
is barbarian. Do you believe?
陛下--
你会
- Well, Your Majesty...
- You will!
如果所有的人都是这么说的话
You will believe I am because
there is no one to speak otherwise.
但这是个谎言
Oh, but this is a lie!
这是个天大的谎言！
It is a false lie!
陛下，你打算怎么办？
What have you decided
to do about it?
你猜猜看
You guess.
好吧
Well,
如果有人在英王面前讲了我的谎话
if someone were sending a lie
about me to England,
我会努力的将事情的真相传到英国
I would do my best to send
the truth to England.
陛下，你也会这么做吧？
Is that what you have decided to do,
Your Majesty?
是的，我是这么打算的，但是怎么做呢？
Yes, that is what I have
decided to do. But how?
但是你猜猜我现在会怎么做呢
Guess how I shall do this.
我一定是想办法
Well, my guess would be
that you would seek
与英国去亲近
some kind of personal contact
with the British.
对了！正好可以利用在这儿访问的大使
Personal contact! When British
ambassador and party arrive in Siam...
英国大使要到这儿吗？
The ambassador, here?
我想他会来的
他们正在做东洋的亲善访问
On quick tour of Orient.
Friendship tour, they say.
莱杰大臣已来报告过了，那么说爱德华也会来？
I receive letters from his aide, Sir
Edward Ramsay, who accompanies him.
爱德华要来？
Edward, coming here?
爱德华？
"Edward"?
你这样称呼他？
You call him this?
我和爱德华是老朋友了，结婚前就认识
We are old friends. I knew him
in London before I was married.
我会对那些侵略者表示出一些想法
When they're here, I'll take
opportunity of expressing my opinion
我要让他们知道
of thieves who would try
to steal my country.
到底谁是野蛮人，野蛮人
I will show them who is barbarian!
你的脸是怎么了？
Well, what is this face you put on?
你是不会和来宾发生冲突的吧
My guess is that you will not fight
with your distinguished visitors.
我当然不会？
是的，陛下
- I will not?
- No, Your Majesty.
我想你会举行一个盛大的宴会
You will give a banquet
in their honor.
非常热情地款待每个人让他们玩得尽兴
You will entertain them in
a particularly grand manner.
这样的话,他们就会知道你是个热心的人
You will make them all
witnesses in your favor.
他们回到英国一定会向女王作善意的报告
They will return to England
and report to the queen
你的善意会证明你不是一个野蛮人
that you are most certainly
not a barbarian.
对！
Naturally!
太对了！当然我就是打算那么做的
Naturally! This is what
I shall have intended to do.
我想，陛下，这个时候
That's it, Your Majesty.
Stand up to them.
你得把自己最好的一面表现出来
Put your best foot forward.
不是表情，陛下
It's an expression, Your Majesty.
我的意思是你最好穿上最华丽的衣服
It means put on your best clothes,
招一些智者和美女出席
show them your most intelligent men
and most beautiful women.
但美女们如果光着脚那又会怎么样呢？
Shall it be proper for the British
to see my women without shoes?
想要加把劲改善一下也不是不可能的吧？
Shall it be proper for my women
to put their best bare feet forward?
不！我想让她们学西方贵族
No, we shall make them look
like ladies of Europe:
在脚上穿上漂亮的鞋子
Shoes on feet, dresses on bodies.
由你来选择这些女孩子穿上洋装
You will tell me which ladies
are most like Europeans
由你来教她们西方的习惯以及礼节
and educate them in European
customs and manner for presentation.
当然，衣物也由你缝制
我缝制？
- Also, sew dresses.
- Sew dresses?
是的，女孩子们会帮你的
All women shall help.
不，陛下…我想就以贵国的
Don't you think it would
make a better impression
服装和礼仪来迎接…
in their own manner and dress?
你说怎么样呀？我们是泰国人，一眼就看得明白
You are not being scientific.
The ambassador knows we are Siamese.
但是想让他们看看我们也接受西方文明
I wish him to know
we are also Europeans.
醒醒！大家到寺庙里集合，快起床吧！
Wake up! Everybody to the temple!
醒醒！妃子，王子，等等，等等！
Wake up, wake up, wives,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
对了，我们还可以表演戏剧、杂技什么的！
We will entertain them with acrobats.
就表演戏剧
We could give them
a theatrical performance.
达布堤改编的"汤姆叔叔的小屋."
Tuptim has written a play, her own
version of Uncle Tom's Cabin.
我们就表演戏剧，让他们知道谁才是野蛮人
We shall give them theatricals.
We'll show them who is barbarian.
晚餐的餐具也是西式的
We could make European dishes
for dinner.
对的，要教他们坐椅子和高脚桌子
You teach. To be served
on high table. Long white tablecloth...
桌面上还要铺白桌布
还有餐巾，用最好的丝绸
- And napkins.
- Of finest silk.
用最好的黄金筷子
筷子？
- Using best gold chopsticks.
- Chopsticks?
不认为刀叉会更合适吗，陛下？
Don't you think knives and forks
would be more suitable?
其实英国的刀叉不如筷子科学
British not scientific enough
for the use of chopsticks.
那么就订制一些金制的刀叉
You are to order finest
gold knives and forks.
还有汤勺
你怎么会忘记汤勺呢？
Also spoons.
Why do you not think of spoons?
陛下，你可真细心
An inspired idea, Your Majesty.
噢，对了，还有雪茄
英国人很喜欢雪茄的
We mustn't forget cigars.
Englishmen are fond of them.
路过和在曼谷的西洋人我也会全部邀请
You are to make list of all eminent
Europeans residing in Bangkok
让他们都来参加宴会
好文章，陛下
- for sending of invitations.
- Very well.
对，你教乐队西方人的舞蹈和…
You will instruct court musicians
their learning music of Europe
音乐怎么样,让他们都学点，等等
for dancing, et cetera,
et cetera, et cetera.
真是好主意，陛下
Excellent, Your Majesty.
那么我有多少时间准备这些？
How much time do I have for all this?
你还有一个星期的时间去准备
British gunboat last reported off
Singkla. This give you one week.
一个星期！陛下，只有一个星期吗？！
One week? Your Majesty, one week!
摩西他曾经说过…
In this same time,
世界是一星期造成的，这可是摩西说的
whole world was created,
Moses say.
来祈求佛祖的保护，下跪吧
First, we ask help from Buddha.
下跪吧！
Bow to him. Bow, bow, bow.
下跪
BOW!
祈祷佛祖，请赐我智慧及力量
Oh, Buddha, give us the aid
of your strength and your wisdom.
祈祷佛祖，请赐我智慧及力量
Oh, Buddha
give us the aid of your strength
祈祷佛祖
and your wisdom.
请赐我智慧及力量向那些英国人证明
And help us to prove
to the visiting English
我们是优秀的民族
that we are extraordinary
and remarkable people.
请帮助我们向那些英国人证明
And help us
to prove to the visiting English
我们是优秀的民族
that we are extraordinary
and remarkable people.
同时也保佑老师昼夜不休尽快将衣服赶制好
Help also Mrs. Anna to keep awake
for scientific sewing of dresses
她虽是个基督教徒
even though she be only
a woman and a Christian,
又是个一无是处的女人…
and therefore unworthy
of your interest.
但请赐给她力量
Help also Mrs. Anna...
陛下，你太过份了--
别忘了，你向我承诺过！
- Your Majesty, this is really--
- A promise is a promise.
你的头不会比我高！
Head must not be higher than mine.
承诺！
A promise!
一无是处
...and therefore
unworthy of your interest.
佛祖
And, Buddha,
当我事成之后我承诺
I promise you
我将为这个女人
that I shall give
this unworthy woman
建一栋房子
a house.
一栋她自己想要的
We will build her a house of her own:
一栋房子
A brick residence
就在皇宫附近
adjoining royal palace
正如契约上所说的
according to agreement,
等等
et cetera,
et cetera.
陛下
- Your Majesty...
- Oh!
为这个一无事外的女人
...this unworthy woman
建一栋房子
a house.
为她建的房子
We will build her
a house of her own.
就在皇宫附近
A brick residence
adjoining royal palace...
正如契约上所说的
...according to agreement...
等等
...et cetera...
...et cetera.
餐巾终于送来了，谢天谢地
张妃，请把它们摆列在餐桌上
The napkins finally arrived. Would
you place them on the table please?
谢谢
不，不必客气
- Thank you.
- No, thank you.
各位，你们都准备好了吗？
客人们就要来了
Are we ready?
The guests are arriving.
安娜夫人，会有英国人来吗
Please, do not let
Englishmen come here.
好可怕呀，安娜夫人
We are afraid.
他们能用眼睛下咒语
They cast terrible spell
on us with evil eye.
求求你了，安娜夫人
Oh, nonsense. Nonsense!
别胡说了,现在，让我来看看
你们准备好了没有
Step back. Let me see how you look.
分开站着
Stand apart.
很好,转圈
Very nice. Now, turn round.
老天！
Oh, my goodness gracious!
怎么啦？
What is trouble now?
我忘记了,她们还没内衣
Oh, I forgot! They have practically
no undergarments.
内衣？有没有穿内衣有什么关系？
Undergarments! Of what importance
are undergarments at this time?
穿内衣是非常重要的
Of great importance.
那么你穿了吗？
Are you wearing undergarments?
所有的英国妇女都会穿内衣的，陛下
All properly dressed English ladies
always wear undergarments.
照你这么说,英国实在是太落伍了
I have opinion that, in this regard,
England is very backward nation.
这是你今晚出
席宴会要穿的吗？
Is this what you shall be wearing?
是的，你喜欢吗？
Why, yes. Do you like it?
那么…
Well...
你这样真的没有关系吗？象这些，等等，等等？
Are you certain this is customary,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera?
你是说露出胸脯？
What is so extraordinary
about bare shoulders?
你看，大家都露了--
- Your own ladies...
- Yes.
但这有些不同…
But is different because
of not wearing
因为你其它的部位都包得很严严实实
covering-ups on other parts
of body, and therefore...
比如说这…但只有,那又怎么样呢？
Therefore what?
不在一样
Is different.
很抱歉，不能得到你的认同
I'm sorry you do not approve.
我可没有那么说
I have not said I do not approve.
陛下，一定是来宾到了
The ambassador and his party
must be arriving.
安娜夫人，他们是食人族吗
Mrs. Anna, Mrs. Anna.
They are cannibals.
会被她们吃掉的
They will eat us!
没那回事
They will do nothing of the kind.
重要的是,当打招呼时
Remember, when you are
presented to the ambassador,
切记别让人看见背后的样子
for heaven's sake, keep your backs
to the wall.
你们明白了吗！
So!
陛下，他是大英帝国的代表强培大使
Your Majesty, this shall be
His Excellency, Sir John Hay,
他特意从英国来拜访你
most honorable representative
of United Kingdom in Great Britain.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
欢迎你
I am pleased.
抽雪茄
Cigar.
谢谢你，陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
国王陛下，
请容我介绍莱杰副使
May I introduce my aide,
Sir Edward Ramsay.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
你好，抽雪茄
I am pleased. Cigar.
谢谢你
Thank you.
啊，她是老师,安娜夫人
And this is Madame Halloweens,
在皇宫里教英语等等的
teacher of English language,
customs, et cetera, in royal household.
久闻大名了，夫人
We've heard of
your splendid work here.
谢谢，大使
Thank you, Your Excellency.
爱德华，好久不见了
Edward, it's so good to see you.
你好，安娜？
How are you, Anna?
跟我来见见我的妃子们，
来吧
Come with me. Meet royal wives.
我的妃子们
Royal wives.
那张脸，是山羊脸！
He has the head of a goat!
邪恶的眼睛！
Evil eye!
邪恶的眼睛
Evil eye! Evil eye!
女士们
- Evil eye!
- Ladies!
各位请回来
噢，亲爱的
Ladies, come back!
Come back. Oh, dear.
陛下，真抱歉出了这种事
Oh, this is dreadful.
你为什么没有教她们还有这种“侦察”眼镜呢？
Why have you not educated them
in the British custom of spying glass?
她们是因为这个受了惊？
Oh, is that what started the panic?
真抱歉，我的妃子们实在太无礼了
I regret, sir, my ladies
have not given good impression.
不，国王陛下
On the contrary.
我今天真的见识到了美妙，这么短的时间里
We have rarely received so good
an impression in so short a time.
安娜，你的学生们真有魅力
You have attractive pupils.
我很想为你们介绍王子和公主们
I wish you could see
His Majesty's children.
但他们现在已经睡了
Unfortunately, they're asleep.
陛下，你有几个孩子呢？
How many children do you have?
只有106个，因为我晚婚了
Oh, I have only 106.
I am not married very long.
下个月，我又会增加五个的
Well, next month,
expecting five more.
安娜，我亲爱的
Anna, my dear.
你比以前任何时候都要美
You're looking lovelier than ever.
好象丝毫没受思乡之苦的折磨
I was hoping to find you wasted
away with homesickness.
因为英国？在那儿已经没令我思念的人了
For England?
I have no one there, Edward.
一个也没有
Not anymore.
一个也没有，安娜？
No one, Anna?
你听？
Hear that?
这是以前我们在里士满共舞过的曲子
We danced to that once.
还记得吗
- Richmond. Remember?
- Mm-hmm.
现在还跳舞吗？
Still dance?
不常跳
Not very often.
那怎么行？
You should.
你应该还记得我曾经向你求过婚？
Do you remember I asked you
to marry me?
是的，汤姆一直以此为豪
Of course. I never allowed Tom
to forget it.
我还没有完全放弃
I never learned to take defeat
like a gentleman.
爱德华
Dear Edward.
我要不是想见自己心爱的人…
I didn't come to Bangkok just because
I enjoy sleeping on a gunboat
本来还不想到这儿来…
or watching Sir John
comb his beard.
安娜，安娜你还是那么年轻…
难道要这样进坟墓吗
Anna, Anna, you're much too young
to bury your heart in a grave.
不，正像你见到的那样
我现在生活得非常好
Oh, but it's not buried.
It's very much alive.
在这里？
是的
- Here?
- Yes.
他们需要我
Among people who need me.
因为我能给他们带来欢乐
People I can help.
你也可以给我带来欢乐
You could help me very much, Anna.
你还要我再等十年吗
I see another 1O years
of waiting in those eyes.
晚餐以后才能跳舞，先生！
Dancing, after dinner!
抱歉，陛下，我们不禁回忆起往事
I'm afraid I couldn't resist
talking over old times.
尽管在这跳舞吧…
I had impression that Mrs. Anna
would help
夫人在餐宴上还有…等等，等等的事要做呢
for seating guests at dinner table,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
现在已经很晚了！大家都站在那等她
Now it is too late.
They all stand up, waiting.
我们最好快入席吧.安娜
In that case, we'd better
be going in, Anna.
对，我们最好赶快入席吧…
Yes. We better be going in...
安娜
...Anna.
我忘了
I forget.
我先告退了，陛下
If you'll excuse me, Your Majesty.
好吧
Huh.
听着，要将这些话题全说出来
Now, herewith, shall be list of
subjects you try to bring up for talk.
我还想发表一些拿手的话题，让来宾心服口服
On such subjects I am very brilliant
and will make great impression.
你从摩西开始
You begin with Moses.
行礼
Bow.
吃啊
Eat, eat, eat!
各位，我记得上次陛下谈到了有关摩西的事
His Majesty made a rather interesting
point about Moses
在他读《圣经》的时候
when he was reading the Bible.
噢，对了
Oh, yes. Now,
我发现了摩西很大的一个破绽…
Moses is very fine illustration
of little-known fact
这是宗教与科学家
that men of faith
and men of science,
无法相容的一个典型的例子
by contradicting each other,
到了最后，我总会找出一些相同的东西
always manage to arrive
at same conclusion.
我来跟你解释
I shall explain...
各位，在此我带头为陛下干杯
I should like to propose a toast.
陛下，泰国的国王
His Gracious Majesty,
the king of Siam:
希望世界各国…
May the rest of the world regard
him with the same high esteem
能以对英国女王的敬意同样尊敬国王陛下
as does the government
of Her Majesty, Queen Victoria.
干杯干杯
Hear! Hear!
陛下
Your Majesty.
我也敬酒，敬酒
More toast.
敬英国及爱尔兰女王
To Her Gracious Majesty, Victoria,
维多利亚女王
Queen of United Kingdom
and Ireland,
遍布全世界的大英帝国的统治者
powerful sovereign of British
colonies around globe of human world.
在此我想表达亲善之意
I wish to say, warm affection.
为了女王，干杯！
To the queen.
请酒到此为止了，请坐
Enough toast for queen. Sit.
现在我们来看些余兴节目
Now, theatricals for entertainment.
今晚
Tonight,
皇室成员之一为了向各位表示敬意
play written by member
of royal palace as surprise for king.
特地改编了一部美国小说
Siamese version
of famous American book.
国王陛下…
Your Majesty
还有各位来宾…
and honorable guests,
你们将欣赏的是…
I beg to put before you:
"汤姆叔叔的小屋"
Small House of Uncle Thomas.
你们将欣赏的是…
We beg to put before you
"汤姆叔叔的小屋."
"Small House of Uncle Thomas"
汤姆叔叔的小屋
Small house of Uncle Thomas,
那是女作家
Written by a woman,
斯陀的小说
Harriet Beecher Stowe.
故事从暴君
House is in Kingdom of Kentucky,
塞蒙王统治的美国
ruled by most wicked king
in all America:
肯塔基的小屋开始
Simon of Legree.
国王陛下
Your Majesty,
现在我来介绍一些善良的人们
I beg to put before you,
loving friends.
汤姆叔叔…
Uncle Thomas.
他是汤姆叔叔
Dear old Uncle Thomas.
可爱的的艾芙…
Little Eva.
他是可爱的艾芙
Blessed little Eva.
小塔西…
Little Topsy.
她是小塔西
Mischief maker, Topsy.
他们快乐地生活着
Happy people.
快乐地生活着
Very happy people.
非常快乐的一群人
Happy, happy, happy people-
国王陛下
Your Majesty...
但是有个人并不快乐
...I beg to put before you
one who is not happy:
她就是奴隶依莱莎
The slave Eliza.
可怜的依莱莎
Poor Eliza,
Poor Eliza.
可怜她是奴隶之身
Poor unfortunate slave.
他的主人就是
Eliza's lord and master:
殖暴的塞蒙
King Simon of Legree.
她非常憎恨主人…
She hates her lord and master...
并且惧怕他
...and fears him.
国王将她的情人卖到遥远的…
This king has sold her lover...
俄亥俄洲去了
...to far away province of Ohio.
她情人的名字叫乔治
Lover's name is George.
乔治
George
她手里抱的孩子也叫乔治
Baby in her arms also called George.
乔治
George
她便决定去找情人乔治…
Eliza say she run away
and look for lover, George.
乔治
George
她告别了朋友…
So she bid goodbye to friends...
然后开始逃亡
...and start on her escape.
她逃走了
The escape.
逃吧，依莱莎
Run, Eliza,
逃离塞蒙
Run from Simon
依莱莎逃进了暴风雨中
Poor Eliza running
and run into a rainstorm.
她来到了高山下
Comes a mountain.
爬吧，依莱莎
Climb, Eliza,
依莱莎来到了森林里
Eliza lose her way in forest.
森林里，迷路了
Hide in forest
可怜的依莱莎
Poor Eliza.
- Poor Eliza
可怜的依莱莎
- Poor Eliza.
Poor Eliza
累极了
Eliza very tired.
陛下
Your Majesty...
现在允许我介绍
...I regret to put before you:
塞蒙王的出场
King Simon of Legree.
因奴隶逃亡塞蒙王便迁怒于每个人
Because one slave has run away,
Simon beating ev'ry slave.
他是一个很狡猾的人
Simon clever man.
为了追回依莱莎
He decide to hunt Eliza...
他不止出动士兵
...not only with soldiers...
他采取更科学的手段…
...but with scientific dogs...
利用猎犬的嗅觉寻找…
...who sniff and smell...
没有任何一个奴隶
能逃离国王
...and thereby discover all
who run from king.
伊莱莎快跑啊
Run, Eliza, run,
快逃，快逃
Run, Eliza, run.
快逃离塞蒙王
Run from Simon, run,
快逃，伊莱莎
Run Eliza
快逃！快逃！
Run, Run
快逃离塞蒙王
Run from Simon
快逃！快逃！
Run, run
可怜的依莱莎
Run Eliza
快逃离塞蒙王
Run from Simon
快逃，伊莱莎
Eliza Run
Run
快逃
Eliza run from Simon
Run
伊莱莎
Run Eliza
快逃离塞蒙王
Run From Simon
快逃，伊莱莎
Run Eliza
快逃离塞蒙王
Run from Simon
快逃，伊莱莎
Run Eliza, run, run
Run
依莱莎来到了河过
Eliza come to river
可怜的依莱莎
Poor Eliza.
谁能拯救她？
Who can save her?
只有佛祖
Only Buddha
请快救依莱莎吧
Save her, Buddha, save her.
佛祖显灵了？
What will Buddha do?
它显灵了
Buddha make a miracle.
佛祖派遣天使下凡来
Buddha send an angel down.
天使吹起冷风时…
Angel make the wind blow cold.
河水就冰冻起来了…
Make the river water hard.
已凝固得可从上面走过
Hard enough to walk upon.
佛祖造的奇迹
Buddha make a miracle.
赞扬佛祖
Praise to Buddha
天使教她行走的方法
Angel show her
how to walk on frozen water.
佛祖为了这伟大的恋情
Now as token of his love...
又制造了一个奇迹…
...Buddha send a new miracle.
赞扬佛祖
Praise to Buddha
从天上飘落的是星星
还是花朵…
Send from heaven, stars...
赞扬佛祖
...and blossoms.
天空中到处飘着白色的蕾丝
Look like lace upon the sky.
赞扬佛祖
Praise to Buddha
有了这些遮掩
So Eliza cross the river...
她平安地度过了河
...hidden by this veil of lace.
我忘了解释这个奇迹…
Forgot to tell you name of miracle.
那就是雪花
Snow!
忽然她看见邪恶的塞蒙王
Of a sudden, she can see
Wicked Simon of Legree...
随后从河上追来带着他的一大群侦探狗
...sliding cross the river fast
with his bloodhounds and his slaves.
河上发生了什么事呢？
What has happened to the river?
佛祖呼唤了艳阳！
Buddha has called out the sun!
冰很快就融化
Sun has made the water soft.
塞蒙王和他的士兵
Wicked Simon and his slaves
都沉到了河底
Fall in river and are drowned.
塞蒙王的人死在河底
Everybody celebrate death of Simon.
依莱莎又回到怀念的汤姆叔叔的小屋
And Eliza make happy reunion
with dear old Uncle Thomas...
跟可爱的伊芙
...blessed little Eva...
她天使般的情人
...mischief maker, Topsy...
乔治也同行
...and faithful lover George...
伊莱莎天使般幸福
...who is looking like Angel to Eliza.
塔西因为国王的死非常高兴
Topsy glad that Simon die
Topsy dance forjoy.
后来塔西也有点反省的雨…
I tell you what Harriet Beecher Stowe
say that Topsy say:
"我定是世界上最坏的孩子吧"
"I specks I'se de wickedest critter
in de world."
但是
But...
但我不认为塔西不对，因为我…
...I do not believe
Topsy is wicked critter...
对国王也有与塔西相同的心情
...because I, too,
am glad for death of king...
我不喜欢折磨，像试图逃跑奴隶
...of any king who pursue a slave who
is unhappy and who tried to escape.
陛下，我想在这告诉你
And Your Majesty,
I wish to say to you:
我求你…
I beg of you!
陛下…
Your Majesty...
各位贵宾…
...and honorable guests...
故事快结束了
...I will tell you end of stow.
是个悲惨的结局，牺牲很大
Is very sad ending, with sacrifice.
可怜的小艾芙
Poor little Eva
她是个不幸的孩子
Poor unfortunate one
佛祖招唤，艾芙回到身过…
ls Buddha's wish
that Eva come to him...
感谢拯救…
...and thank him personally...
依莱莎母女之恩赐
...for saving of Eliza and baby.
所以她死去.
And so she die...
回到了佛祖的身边
...and go to arms of Buddha.
赞扬佛祖
Praise to Buddha
很好，非常好，国王陛下
Very clever.
Very clever, Your Majesty.
实在是很有创新
Author! Author!
很有创意
Ah.
陛下，就寝之前我来请示还有什么要做？
Is there anything else
before I say good night?
坐下，坐下
Sit, sit, sit.
请随便吃点
Plenty for two. Eat.
不用了，谢谢
Oh, no, thank you.
叉子真是一件奇妙的餐具啊
Fork is a foolhardy instrument.
装满食物时就会漏下来
You pick up food, and it leaks.
陛下，你在宴会时的谈话真风趣
Oh, your conversation at dinner
was most amusing, Your Majesty.
我自己也觉得，我自己非常地有趣！
I was forced to laugh myself.
I was so funny.
对了，爱德华和大使也很佩服你
Before leaving, Edward confided that
the ambassador was quite impressed.
爱德华
Edward.
他们一定会向女王作善意的报告的
And he will most certainly send
a glowing report to Queen Victoria.
这样我也就安心了，陛下
I am so pleased, Your Majesty.
你做得很好
I am aware of your interest.
我想说…
I wish to say...
我想说这次的
事你帮了不少忙
...you have been of great help
to me in this endeavor.
这是我的一点心意
I wish to make gift.
你收下吧
I have hope you accept.
戴在你的手上
Put it on.
Put it on finger.
快点戴上，快点戴上
Oh, put it on,
put it on, put it on.
陛下，我不知道该说些什么才好
Your Majesty,
I don't know what to say.
当一个人不知道
说些什么的时候
When one does not know
what to say...
最好是什么都别说
...it is a time to be silent.
现在很晚了，陛下，
如果没有别的事的话，我想--
It is late, Your Majesty.
If there's nothing else--
不，还有一件事
There is, there is, there is else.
有一个好消息
Have good news to tell.
昨天晚上在西犹塔森林发现了白象
Yesterday, a white elephant has been
discovered in forest of Ayutthaya.
这是个好预兆吗，陛下
And you regard this as a good omen?
是的，是非常好的预兆
Yes. Very good omen.
什么事都将会很顺利
Everything going well with us?
是的，一定会这样的，陛下，我们一切进展顺利
Yes, everything going well with us.
达布堤，你的学生！
Tuptim, your pupil.
她今晚编的戏
我却觉得不太好
Her play tonight.
但是，陛下，来宾都很喜欢
Oh, but, Your Majesty,
everyone enjoyed it immensely.
让追奴隶的国王淹死这是怎么回事！
It is immoral for king to drown
when pursuing slave who deceive him.
这是天大的不敬！
Immoral. Immoral!
找到她时，得好好惩罚她一下才行
Tuptim shall hear of my displeasure
when she is found.
找她？
Found?
她好像藏在宫中的某个地方…
It is believed she hides
somewhere in palace...
以逃避国王的不悦
...to escape king's anger and...
安娜，我想你应该知道点什么吧
You know something of this?
她是个可怜的姑娘，陛下
住在宫里有什么可怜的？！
- Only that she has been unhappy.
- Why unhappy?
她应该感到荣幸才对
She is in palace of king!
年轻的女孩，没有比这更高兴的了
What is greater honor for girl
than to be in palace of king?
但是，陛下，你有这么多的事要做
你何必在意她呢？
Oh, but, Your Majesty, of what interest
to you is one girl like Tuptim?
反正她只是你几十个女人当中的一个
In your house,
she's just another woman.
一个碗里的大米跟另一个碗的大米没区别
As a bowl of rice is just another bowl
of rice, no different from any other.
你现在是站在女人的一边了！
Now you understand about women.
书上写得那些爱情她们竟会当真
So many English books I read
introduce strange idea...
天啊，好笑极了
...of love,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
你不赞成那些观点？
You disapprove?
但其实她什么也不懂
But it is a silly complication
of a pleasant simplicity.
女人是为了取悦男人而活的，就是这样
A woman is designed for pleasing man.
That is all.
众多的女人要服侍男人这才是天经地义
A man is designed to be pleased
by many women.
这就是你的解释吗，陛下
How do you explain the fact,
Your Majesty...
这个世界上还有很多的男人只娶一个妻子？
...that many men remain faithful
to one wife?
那是有病
They are sick.
只有女人得守贞操吗
But you do expect women
to be faithful.
-那当然了
-为什么？
- Naturally.
- Well, why naturally?
因为这是自然的事情
Because it is natural.
泰国有首这样的诗…
It is like old Siamese rhyme:
女人是朵花
A girl must be like a blossom
只供一个男人去采蜜
with honey for just one man.
男人是蜜蜂
A man must live like honeybee
忙碌在花丛中采取花蜜
and gather all he can.
在花丛中穿来穿去
To fly from blossom to blossom,
从来不受任何阻扰
A honeybee must be free,
花朵只能静候蜜蜂的来访
But blossom must not ever fly
采蜜，采蜜
from bee, to bee, to bee.
陛下，我的国家就完全不同了
Oh, Your Majesty, in my
country we have a far different attitude.
对我们来说，一个真正快乐的男人
We believe that
for a man to be truly happy...
他只能一心一意爱一个女人
...he must love one woman
and one woman only.
这是妇人之见
This idea was invented by woman.
但是个很美好的念头
But it's a beautiful idea,
Your Majesty.
我们都是相信这个长大的
In England, we're brought up with it.
当年轻女孩初次参加舞会时
And by the time a young girl
goes to her first dance--
年轻女孩
Young girl?
也跳舞吗？
They dance also?
就像我今晚看见的那样
被不是丈夫的男人搂着跳舞？
Like tonight?
In arms of man not her husband?
当然了
Why, of course.
我绝对不允许
I would not permit.
那真让人感到兴奋
Oh, but it's very exciting.
当年轻人
When you're young...
生平参加的第一次舞会.
...at your first dance...
你一直都坐在一把小椅子是…
...and you're sitting
on a small gilt chair...
低垂着眼
...with your eyes lowered...
内心里一直担心会没人邀请跳舞
...terrified that you'll be
a Wallflower.
然后忽然你看见两只黑皮鞋
And suddenly you see
two black shoes...
和一套白背心的人
...a white waistcoat...
出现了，它的脸，在诉说着
...a face. It speaks.
刚刚才介绍过的
We've just been introduced,
我并不认识你
I do not know you well.
但当音乐响起时，不觉的被吸引到你身边
But when the music started,
something drew me to your side.
所以一对对的男男女女
So many men and girls
手臂相挽的跳着舞
Are in each other's arms,
它让我想到
It made me think
我们也可以
we might be
加入那个圈子
similarly occupied.
我们来跳舞吧
Shall we dance?
随着轻快的音乐，舞上云霄
On a bright cloud of music shall we fly?
我们来跳舞吧？
Shall we dance?
直跳到晚安道别前
Shall we then say "goodnight"
and mean "goodbye?"
或许
Oh, perchance
舞到最后星星消失时
when the last little star
has left the sky.
我们还能手挽着手
Shall we still be together
with our arms around each other,
你就成为我的新恋人？
And shall you be my new romance?
我早就已经有了那种预感
On the clear understanding
that this kind of thing can happen,
我们来跳舞好吗？
Shall we dance?
你为什么要停下来呢？继续跳啊，跳啊
Why do you stop?
You dance pretty. Go on.
陛下，我没意识到，再说了，我又不是个舞娘
Your Majesty, I didn't realize.
After all, I'm not a dancing girl.
在英国，没有女人会
当着一个男人的面独自跳舞
In England, no woman dances alone
while a man looks on.
但你们和那些不认识的男人跳舞啊
手挽着手，等等
But she dances with stranger,
holding hands?
是的，但并不经常都是陌生人--
Yes, but not always a stranger.
也会有我们的好朋友
很好，那我们现在就来跳吧
- Usually a very good friend.
- Then we'll dance together.
你来教我吧
我来和你跳，怎么样？
You show me.
Teach, teach, teach.
好的，那是很简单的
It's quite simple, the polka.
数着1，2，3，就行了.1，2，3
You count, "One, two, three,
and one, two, three...
1，2，3…
...and one, two, three, and..."
我们来跳舞吧
Shall we dance?
1，2，3…
One, two, three, and.
随着轻快的音乐飞上云霄
On a bright cloud of music shall we fly?
1，2，3…
One, two, three, and.
我们来跳舞吧？
Shall we dance?
1，2，3…
One, two, three, and.
直跳到晚安说道别前
Shall we then say "goodnight"
and mean "goodbye?"
1，2，3…
One, two, three, and.
或许
Oh, perchance
舞到最后的星星消失时
when the last little star has left the sky.
我们还是在一起手挽着手
Shall we still be together
with our arms around each other,
你就会成为我的新恋人
And shall you be my new romance?
我早就意识到那会发生
On the clear understanding
that this kind of thing can happen,
我们来跳舞吧？
Shall we dance?
现在数1，2，3，
1，2，3--
- And one, two, three--
- One, two, three, one, two, three--
有点怪怪的
Something wrong.
我忘了节拍，下次我会记得的
I know, I forgot "and."
Next time I remember.
1，2，3，
1，2，3
One, two, three,
and one, two, three--
你跳得很好，陛下
That's splendid, Your Majesty.
很好，很好
Splendid, splendid!
你把我的节奏给弄乱了
You throw me off count!
1，2，3
And, one, two, three, and
one, two, three, and...
有点不对
That is not right.
不，这样就对了
就是这样
You were doing beautifully,
Your Majesty.
这和今晚我看到你跟那个西方人跳的不同
No, no. Not the way I see
Europeans dancing tonight.
不，就是这样跳的
Yes, it was. It was just like that.
不是这样的手好像不是这样握的
Were not holding two hands like this.
这…
No...
的确不是这样的
...as a matter of fact.
应该是…
Was...
这样，不是吗
...like this?
是吗？
No?
是的
Yes.
跳吧
Come.
来
我们再来一次
We do it again.
陛下
你为什么要来打扰我呢？
- Your Majesty--
- Why do you burst in here?
找到达布堤了
We have found Tuptim.
她在哪？
现在还在调查中
- Where is she?
- Secret police are questioning her.
但那个男的还没抓到
Her lover has not been caught.
Not yet.
她的什么？
What?
那个要和达布堤一起私奔的就是伦塔
It is believed she was
running away with Lun Tha...
送她来这儿的缅甸使者
...man who bring her here
from Burma.
这是何等的耻辱
Dishonor.
Dishonor. Dishonor!
把她带上来
但是，陛下，你想对她怎么样？
- Bring her in.
- Your Majesty, what will you do?
我会让她知道厉害的
I shall do what is usually done
in such event.
不，不
No. No!
不要，安娜夫人，让他们不要罚我！
No! Mrs. Anna,
do not let them beat me.
让他们不要！
Do not let them!
男的在那？
我不知道
- Where is this man?
- I do not know.
你早就和那个男的相好了
It is known you were lovers with him.
我是冤枉的！
I was not lovers with this man!
不知羞耻的贱人
Dishonor!
会让你招供的！
住手！听见了没有？
- We will have truth of you.
- Stop that! Do you hear? Stop it!
你能明白就再好不过了
It is better
if you understand at once...
这件事与你无关
...that this does not concern you.
我是为陛下着想,所以不能袖手旁观…
Oh, but it does, Your Majesty.
It does, dreadfully.
为她，更是为您
Because of her,
and even more because of you.
她只是个孩子,我想她是因为不快乐才逃走的
She's a child, running away
because she was unhappy.
陛下，你放过她吧？
Can't you understand that?
你是在浪费时间！
You waste my time!
陛下，请您想想即使你惩罚她又能怎么样呢
I beg of you not to take revenge
on this girl.
那只会将你一直以来的努力全部化为乌有
You'll throw away everything you've
accomplished for yourself and country.
而你只是因为虚荣心受伤,她并没有伤着你的心
The girl hurt your vanity, that's all.
She didn't hurt your heart.
你没有爱心！
You have no heart!
也从来没有爱过任何人！
You've never loved anyone
and you never will.
把鞭子给我！给我！
I will show you. Give me.
我真不敢相信你真的想打她吗
I can't believe you will do
this dreadful thing!
不相信，是吗？等你听到哀嚎之后就会夺门而出了！
You don't? Believe when you hear
her screams as you run from here.
我不会逃走的，要待在这看到最后
I am not going to run. I am going
to stand here and watch you.
这个女人由我亲自来处罚
Hold this girl. I do this myself!
你是个野蛮人
You are a barbarian.
趴下，趴下
Down, down, down!
当我是国王了吗？
Am I king or am I not king?
在我的王宫里不允许有这种事发生
我没有义务听一个教师的指示
Am I to be cuckold in my own palace,
to take orders from English teacher?
不，陛下，这不是指示
闭嘴！
- No, no. Not orders.
- Silence!
我打从娘胎里下来就是国王了
I am king as I was born to be...
我要以自己的方式来治理我的王国--
...and Siam to be governed
in my way!
而不是英国或者法国或者是中国的那些方式！
Not English way, not French way,
not Chinese way!
以我自己的方式！
My Way!
你说我是个野蛮人
Barbarian, you say.
那总要比那个软弱的国王要好得多
There is no barbarian worse
than a weak king.
现在我让你见识一下我的强壮？
And I am strong, do you hear?
我的强壮
Strong!
怎么回事？
Well?
男人的尸体在河中被发现了
The man, the lover has been found
in river. He is dead.
他死了
Dead?
噢，不
Oh, no!
我真的无法理解
你们还有国王
I don't understand you,
not you or your king.
我不理解你们
I'll never understand him.
你！
YOU!
我怕发生这种事故,早就警告过你
When I warn you of this
many months ago, you do not listen.
你毁了他
You have destroyed him.
陛下已不是从前的陛下了
He can never be the king
he was before.
都是你把国王变得软弱了
You have taken all that
away from him.
都是因为你
You have destroyed king!
不管上哪都行,我要搭下班船走
The next boat that comes, no matter
where it goes, I shall be on it.
我要走，请把这个还给国王
Give this back to His Majesty.
你不应该到这儿来
I wish you have never come to Siam.
是的
So do I.
我不应该到这儿来
Oh, so do I!
妈妈
Mother.
妈妈，我们的行李已经准备好了
Mother, our luggage is all loaded.
船也快要开了
We'll be late for the boat.
好的，路易
Yes, Louis.
我立刻就去
I'm coming.
安娜夫人
Mrs. Anna.
张妃，谢谢你
Lady Thiang. Your Highness.
来为我送行
How nice of you
to come to say goodbye.
不，我不是来送行的
Mrs. Anna, I do not come for myself.
我是希望你立刻去见陛下
I come for one
who must see you quickly.
你应该告诉他我现在已经不是他的仆女
You may tell His Majesty
I am no longer subject to him.
你什么也不知道
You do not understand.
安娜夫人…
Mrs. Anna...
他快死了
...he is dying!
快死了？
Dying?
陛下？
The king?
不，张妃，出什么事了？
Oh, no, Lady Thiang.
What happened?
没人知道是怎么回事？
Who can say what it is
that makes a man die?
他一定是过度忧伤而招致死亡的
A sad heart that no longer wishes
to go on beating?
那天晚宴后，他就避开人
Ever since night of great banquet,
he has shut himself away in palace...
封闭在自己的世界里
...turning from all
who would speak to him...
不吃不睡，废寝忘食的看着书…
...unwilling to sleep
or to nourish himself...
并时时地叹息着
...searching through many books,
only to push them aside in despair.
御医劝了他很多次…
Doctors warned him he must
change his ways quickly...
但他都不听，安娜夫人
...but he would not listen, Mrs. Anna.
他完全不听别人的劝告
He would not listen.
我怎么什么都不知道呢
I had no idea.
因为他禁止将这件事张扬出去…
Everyone who knew
was forbidden to speak of it.
御医说这是迟早的问题
And now,
doctors have no hope for him.
安娜夫人
Mrs. Anna.
殿下
Your Highness.
我很害怕，安娜夫人
I am frightened, Mrs. Anna.
因为我很爱父王…
I am frightened
because I love my father...
如果他死了我就得继承王位
...and also because if he dies,
I shall be king.
我应该怎么样去当国王？
And I do not know how to be.
孩子，等你当国王后再学习也不晚，真的
Many men learn this after
they become kings, Your Highness.
你只要把老师教过你的事再回想一下
It will be good to think back...
国王交给我这封信
...on all that
Mrs. Anna has taught you.
希望在你离开前交给你
When king heard you were sailing
tonight, he started to write letter.
他非常困难地
完成了这封信…
It was difficult for him, Mrs. Anna.
非常困难
Very difficult.
他要我转交给你
He has commanded
that I give it to you.
安娜夫人，你能把信念给我们听听吗？
Please, may I hear what
my father has said, Mrs. Anna?
"你好，安娜
"While I am lying here...
"看来我活不久了
...I think perhaps I die.
"虽然我从没想到
This heart which you say
I have not got...
"这会发生得这么快
...is matter of concern.
"对我来说死应该是很平常的事
"It occurs to me that there shall be
nothing wrong that men shall die.
"我也没有什么好遗憾的
"For all that matters about man...
"问题在于我是否做到了最好
...is that he shall have tried
his utmost best.
"想想你也为本国
In looking back, I discover that
you think much on those people
尽了最大的努力
...who require that you live up
to best of self.
"因为你经常会说出实话
You have spoken truth
to me always...
"所以有时我会感到很气愤
...and for this I have often
lost my temper on you.
"但是安娜,在我死之前
But now I do not wish to die...
"我诚心向你表示感谢
...without saying this gratitude...
以及等等的
...and large respect,
et cetera, et cetera.
"安娜，你以女子之躯…
"I think it very strange...
"竟然那么能干…
...that a woman shall have been
most earnest help of all.
"可是，安娜，你要知道…
But, Mrs. Anna,
you must remember...
"你真的是个很顽固的女人…
...that you have been
a very difficult woman...
"我认为没有别的女人会向你一样，与众不同
...and much more difficult
than generality."
我们得回去了
We must hurry back now.
你会来吗？
You will come?
妈妈
Mother...
现在国王快死了
...now that the king is dying...
你们会和好吗？
...does that make you friends again?
是的，路易斯
I suppose so, Louis.
我们不能再彼此伤害了
We can't hurt each other anymore.
他是个可怕的人
He always frightened me.
如果你了解他的话
I wish you had known him better.
一定会和他成为朋友的
You two could have been
such good friends.
他有些地方很孩子气
In many ways he was
just as young as you.
你认为他是个好国王吗？
Was he as good a king
as he could have been?
是的，我认为再也没有比他更好的国王了
I don't think any man has ever been
as good a king as he could have been.
他都尝试过了
But this one tried.
而且非常的努力
He tried very hard.
你喜欢国王是吗，妈妈？
You really like him,
don't you, Mother?
是的，路易
Yes, Louis.
我非常喜欢他…
I like him very much.
非常喜欢
Very much indeed.
几个星期没见你了…
Several weeks...
安娜夫人
...I do not see you, Mrs. Anna.
我快死了
And now I die.
不会的，陛下
Oh, no, Your Majesty.
这是很不科学的回答
This is not scientific.
我知道…
I know...
自己什么时候死
...if I die or do not die.
你不该来的，你不回自己的寝室吗？
You shouldn't be here.
Can't we move you to your room?
不
No.
这个房间比较好，这里是知识的宝库
I wish to remain here
in room with knowledge.
你要回国了？
You are leaving Siam?
什么时候走
When?
很快就走，陛下
Very soon, Your Majesty.
我只能在这儿逗留一会儿，
陛下
In fact, I can stay
only a few more minutes.
你很高兴吗？
And you are glad of this?
泰国的人民…
People of Siam...
王子，公主们
...royal children, et cetera...
他们并不高兴
...are not glad.
大家因为你要回国…
And all are in great affliction...
而感到很悲伤，很难过
...of your departure.
我会相信他们的
I shall miss them.
你会相信他们的
You shall miss them...
但是你要走了
...but you shall be leaving.
我，也是
I, too...
要走了
...am leaving.
只是不用乘船…
Only I'm not walking onto a boat...
甚至不是我自己的意志
...with my own feet...
我要走了
...of my own free will.
是该走了
I am just leaving.
你的头为什么要比我高？
Why is your head higher than mine?
这个
Here.
是你的
Here is something belonging to you.
戴上
Put it on.
把它戴上！
戴上！
Put it on, put it on.
请你
Please...
戴上它
...wear it.
孩子们来了
The children.
孩子们靠近我
Let my children come in.
晚安，孩子们
Good evening, children.
晚安，父皇
Good evening, my father.
老师，请你别走！
- Please, do not go. We'll miss you!
- Children!
孩子们，不可以
Stop this noise.
你们是来探望父王还是安娜夫人
Did you come to see your father
or Mrs. Anna?
没关系的，张妃
It is all right, Lady Thiang.
难怪他们会这样
It is suitable.
父王
My father.
什么事，雅欧拉克
Princess Ying Yaowalak.
我想请求你…
I have wish to--
她是想传话给安娜夫人
She has memorized message
for Mrs. Anna.
你说吧
Speak message now.
说吧
Say it, say it, say it.
我们的良师良友
Dear friend and teacher...
拜托你
...my goodness gracious...
别离去
...do not go away.
因为我们都需要你
We are in great need of you.
我们就像眼睛看不见的盲人
We are like one blind.
求你别弃我们于黑暗不顾
Do not let us fall down in darkness.
再象以前般温柔的…
Continue good and sincere...
守护并指引
...concern for us...
我们上正道
...and lead us in right road.
你的学生
Your loving pupil...
雅欧拉克公主
...Princess Ying Yaowalak.
妈妈
Mother...
船要开了我们走吧
...it's the boat. It's time to go.
请不要走，安娜夫人
- Do not go, Mrs. Anna.
- Please do not go.
安娜夫人，你别走
No, no, Mrs. Anna!
路易，马上告诉船长把行李卸下，快点拿回来
Run down to the boat and ask
Captain Orton to take our things off.
是的，妈妈
Yes, Mother.
安静
Silence!
这没什么好兴奋的
There's no reason
for doing of demonstration...
她只是尽了老师的职责而矣
...for schoolteacher
realizing her duty...
而且我还付给她高薪呢…
...for which I pay her
exorbitant monthly fee...
一个月…
...of...
25英磅
...twenty-five pounds.
还有…
Furthermore...
在临死国王的枕边…
...this is disorganized behavior...
如此的吵闹，实在是不敬
...in presence of dying king.
皇太子…
Chulalongkorn.
站起来
Rise.
安娜夫人
Mrs. Anna...
你
...you...
来当书记
...take notes.
记下我的笔录…
You take notes...
说给下一任国王
...from next king.
好吧
Well?
如果你当了国王
Suppose you are king.
会怎么样呢？
Is there nothing you would do?
我
I...
我会下令
...would make proclamations.
是的。什么令呢？
Yes. Yes?
首先，我会在过年时
First, I would proclaim
for coming New Year...
放烟火
...fireworks.
哈哈
Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm.
还要举办划舟竞赛
Also boat races.
划舟竞赛？
Boat races?
为什么要在新年举办划舟竞赛呢？
Why boat races
with New Year's celebration?
我喜欢划舟竞赛呢
I like boat races.
然后我会下第二道命令
And, Father, I would make
second proclamation.
好的，什么是第二道命令？
说说看
Yes, what is second proclamation?
Make it, make it.
这种象青蛙似的向国王行礼…
Regarding custom
of bowing to king...
要废除掉
...in fashion of lowly toad.
我认为
I do not believe this is good thing.
勉强别人不是一件好事
Causing embarrassing fatigue
of body...
会让国民的心卑微
...degrading experience for soul...
等等，等等
...et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
很不好…
This is bad thing.
我觉得应该废除掉
I believe.
你会对我生气吗，父王？
You are angry with me, my father?
为什么要问这种事呢？
Oh, why do you ask question?
只要继续位了
If you are king...
你就是国王！
...you are king!
别问一个生病的人…
Don't ask question of sick man.
还有
Nor...
女人的意见
...of woman.
也想废除…
This proclamation...
对国王伏地下跪的事…
...against bowing to king...
要由你来负责
...I believe to be your fault.
要真能那样做就好了
Oh, I hope so, Your Majesty.
我早就盼望着有这一天了
I do hope so.
大家站起来
Up! Rise up!
父王？
Father?
起来，起来
Up,up,up!
像士兵一样排成一队
Like soldiers in lines.
就像他刚才说的一样…
It has been said.
今后表示敬意时…
There shall be no more bowing...
不用这样
...for showing...
对国王
...respect...
行礼
...for king.
那是治理国家的王者…
It has been said by one...
富有经验的智者…
...who has been trained...
所说的
...for royal...
至理明言
...government.
今后不必象青蛙一样行礼
There shall be no bowing like toad.
不再蹲伏
No crouching.
不再爬行
No crawling.
但并不是要你们不尊敬国王
This does not mean, however,
that you do not show respect for king.
你们要像这样挺起胸膛…
You will stand with shoulders back...
抬起头。就像这样
...and chin high, like this.
像国王一样气宇轩昂
You will face king
with proud expression...
像国王一样高傲
...showing pride in self
as well as in king.
相互尊重才是正确的礼仪
This is proper way for men
to show esteem for one another...
眼睛和眼睛相对才有人性的尊严
...by looking upon each other's faces
with calmness of spirit...
平等的凝望
...eyes meeting eyes in equal gaze...
像个男人般挺胸站立
...bodies upright, standing as men
were meant to stand...
平等尊重
...with dignity and awareness of self.
从现在开始
So from this day forward...
本版本字幕由 Wendy's PaPa 翻译、整理、调校时间轴
This version subtitles by Wendy's PaPa